software engineering radio episode 70 X
unit test patterns with Jared Meszaros
welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode Martine is going to talk to
Jerrod Meszaros about X unit test
patterns Gerrard has written a book on
this topic it's called X unit test
patterns it's published in Martin
Fowler's Signature Series with
addison-wesley Gerrard is also going to
host and present a tutorial at this
year's oops law conference and as you
know we've been corporate using the oops
lab podcast together with SEO radio and
as you've heard before this one is an
extended version of the interview that
we've done for the oops lab podcast so
if you hear Martin reference the
tutorial this of course means the
tutorial he's going to give a loop slab
and all the stuff that he's going to
talk about dupes livened for the book so
have fun listening and please welcome
Martin I would like to ask you Jarrett
to introduce yourself okay well I'm a an
agile software development coach working
with Clearstream consulting in Calgary
Alberta Canada I've had it's about 25
years experience in the software
development industry starting with
writing telephone switching software and
have transitioned to sort of more
traditional business IT software in the
last 11 or 12 years we started doing
extreme programming and other agile
methods of in about 2000 and that's
where we first encountered writing
automated tests using X unit in that
case it was J unit but we've written
them in a number of other variants of
the X unit family as well since then so
what are you going to talk about at oops
I already mentioned tutorial about with
unit testing stuff can you can you tell
us a bit more about it yeah sure my
tutorial is on X unit testing patterns
it's called X unit test patterns and
smells
and the basic idea is that tests are
great to have but that you really have
to be concerned about the
maintainability of those tests and if
the tests are constantly breaking or if
the tests are really hard to understand
it takes a lot of energy to both write
and maintain those tests and that will
discourage people from continuing to to
write and maintain tests and the big
issue there is that unlike production
code which you don't have a choice but
to maintain tests are optional and you
can always just stop running them and
just throw them away and any investment
you've made in writing all those
automated tests just goes out the window
so it's really important to focus on
writing good quality tests that are
robust and repeatable and easy to
understand
so the tutorial is about the various
kinds of smells that you would encounter
while maintaining test code and the
patterns that you can use to avoid them
you also wrote a book about it
is it correct that's correct last three
years of my life have been spent writing
this book I put off writing it for a
while I was hoping someone else would
write it but after several years no one
had stepped into the void so finally I
just bit the bullet and started and it
it grew to be a lot bigger than I ever
expected I like to joke that the book is
so thick because it had twice the
gestation period of an elephant
so what what motivated you to write the
book and to run the tutorial well I work
with a lot of different clients who are
taking up agile methods and of course
the thing that developers always jump on
is the automated unit testing I often
get brought in well it's sort of two
models either get brought in by
enlightened companies to help them start
the project off on the right foot or
companies that are having difficulty
they tried it by themselves
you know their project is in trouble
I'll get brought in to help them dig
themselves out of the hole in the latter
case what I often see is that they
either don't have very many tests or the
test that they have are consuming an
inordinate amount of time to write and
maintain and we learned fairly early on
in our experience of trying XP when we
first started in 2000 that you can very
easily dig yourself into a big hole by
making some wrong decisions about how
you go about automating the tests and
the tests can easily take you know 70 80
90 percent of your development time
where they should be taking 10 or 20
percent of your development time and you
should be saving that all back by a
reduced amount of debugging of your
production code so having seen this
recurring theme that everywhere we went
we were looking at all these tests they
were really hard to understand
they were just begging for refactoring
and cleaning up we said well how can we
help the community by you know helping
them understand how to do this right the
first time rather than creating all
these ugly tests and then trying to
figure out a way to back away from those
tests and you know turn them into more
maintainable tests so we started off by
one of our clients asked us if we could
produce a course to present to all their
staff and we did we created a two day
course on the idea of how you go about
doing automated developer testing using
in that case it was j-unit and then the
ideas of that course evolved into more
expanded form into the book and in a
more condensed form into the tutorial
I'm presenting a group saw why our test
from your point of view so crucial so
everybody talks about j-unit and some
people use it using unit testing
frameworks and some people are not using
them and some people do test-driven
development some people do not so what
what is your
opinion on why our test so crucial well
the role of tests and particularly
automated unit tests in agile methods is
a means to both focus the developers on
what needs to be done so it's a it's
part of the discipline that that we
apply in agile methods as opposed to
document driven methods the discipline
is about writing these huge big
documents in agile methods the
discipline is around writing the the
automated tests and before you write the
code writing the test gives you a way to
reason about what the software should do
so the tests become your requirements
spec they describe what a particular
object or class should do for you what
its inputs should be what its outputs
should be in response to those inputs
whether it's state fuller stateless and
so on and then once you've written the
production code to pass those tests the
tests acting as a definition of what
done looks like then from then on those
tests act as a regression test safety
net and the key thing there is in an XP
for example the mantra is if you can
delete code and no tests fail great you
just reduced the amount of code to
maintain if you are if you're not sure
what the impact of a change will be
rather than you know spending hours
analyzing the code and trying to figure
out what would happen if you made the
change you just make the change and the
tests will tell you the number of tests
that fail tells you how big an impact
that particular change has so it leads
to a much more interactive feedback rich
experimental style of writing code
rather than a lot of you know sitting in
the corner you know thinking thinking
thinking and hopefully getting all
everything sort of into your head you
you don't have to keep as much in your
head while you're working and it makes
software development a lot more
enjoyable when you have tests acting as
a safety net for you and at the end it's
about it's about feet big isn't it it's
all about feedback the tests are your
feedback because every time you you you
know save your code compile it and run
the test the tests are giving you
feedback like when I'm writing code in
Eclipse I have it set up so every time I
press save it automatically runs all the
tests so I get feedback you know every
20 seconds minute five minutes at most
is I'm typing away I know exactly what
the score is and especially when you're
doing the highly incremental style of
test-driven development advocated by you
know people I can't back in Dave asked
Olson company they you know would say
write one test make the code pass that
test write the next test etc so you're
constantly just sort of increasing the
specification and keep writing just
enough code to pass it and it also is a
form of reverse code coverage because
you never write code that you don't need
in order to pass a test one of the big
gotchas that a lot of people get into is
they write a whole bunch of code and
then they ask how do i unit test this
trying to retrofit unit testability onto
code that you've already written is
really hard because that means you have
to think about design for testability in
the abstract and you know that kind of
planning ahead you know even if it's 90%
successful the 10% that you didn't think
about it's going to get you and make it
really hard to test by writing your
tests first the tests force the software
you're writing to be testable so you're
thinking about testability before you
write the software and that makes
testability of the software just so much
easier and means also that a you're not
coming to the the situation where you
think about oh I don't have enough time
now I'll let's skip the automated unit
tests if you write them before right
exactly yeah and and because you have
the tests these spent very little time
and debuggers if you're spending a lot
of time in debuggers that's telling you
that you don't have the right unit tests
in place because the tests aren't
forcing you to write the correct
software but rather you're writing a
bunch of software and then you're single
stepping through trying to figure out
what the software is doing well that's a
symptom of missing unit tests
if we talk about this is kind of unit
testing it sounds to me pretty much like
there are two different kinds of code
there's a production code that goes into
the system and there's the the unit test
code so all those codes different or how
do you how do you see the the difference
between those two kinds of code yeah
they're very different production code
by its very nature needs to handle a
whole bunch of different scenarios so it
tends to have a lot of conditional logic
in it if statements loops switch
statements
you know lots of dynamic dispatching if
you're doing object oriented like domain
driven design so there's an essential
complexity to production code the
difference with test code is that it
should be dead simple test code should
be completely linear because each test
should test the system and exactly what
exactly one path through the systems the
way to think about it right if the
system is in a certain state whatever
the system is you know an individual
class for example and I invoke a certain
method honor with a certain set of
arguments I should be able to predict
ahead of time exactly what the output
should be in terms of you know response
return values updated parameters etc and
exactly what the afterword state should
be so that's a very linear sequence of
statements there shouldn't be any
conditional logic in there because the
test should test one scenario you'll
have many little tests rather than one
big ball of mud as Brian foot would call
it which is your production code but
still there there's some some
similarities between those those two
kinds of codes right well the similarity
is that they're both written in the same
language typically that's one of the
reasons why X unit is so popular if
you're a Java developer you develop your
test in in Java and J unit and so on and
some of the same techniques can be used
within the software to manage complexity
and some of the same refactorings of the
code can be used to transform hard to
understand
easier to understand code but you know
beyond those similarities in fact the
test code is quite different from the
production code this is part of the
challenge for a lot of developers is
they're used to engineering highly
complicated convoluted clever production
code to solve tough problems and they've
sort of evolved the simplicity gene out
of their heads and and they will
naturally apply the same kind of
complexity to the tests but the problem
is you're gonna have typically at least
as much test code as production code and
often several times as much test code as
production code and if you have to put
the same kind of effort into
understanding the test code as the
production code mm-hmm and the same kind
of effort into writing the test code as
the production code you've just doubled
or tripled the cost of producing your
software and no one can afford that I
mean you know even with the improvement
in quality that all this automated
testing brings you really cannot afford
to have double or triple the cost of
producing the code it has to come out
roughly the same and that's why the test
code has to be kept simple simple simple
right it's got to be really clean and
simple and that makes writing the code
easy and it makes understanding the code
easy and that's what a lot of these
patterns are all about is how do you
structure the test code in such a way
that it's easy to write test after test
after test because you've elevated the
language of testing from Java or C sharp
or whatever to something more more like
a domain-specific language for testing
your particular application doesn't mean
that I should apply similar techniques
to like like I do apply to my production
system like refactoring code to make it
simpler and trying to find refactorings
by finding code smelts and then those
those techniques absolutely and so
they're just like in production code you
can either write clean code to start or
you can write messy code whatever you
know first make it work and then
refactor it to improve the design
and by knowing what the patterns are you
have a better chance of writing clean
code to start with but then there's a
bunch of tests refactorings you can use
to get from messy test code to clean
simple maintainable test code so they're
the parallel is complete it's it's
exactly the same issues with production
code the key difference from an agile
developers perspective though is that
when you're refactoring production code
you have tests that protect you while
you're doing the refactoring when you're
refactoring the tests you don't have
that same protection so you have to be a
little bit more careful when you're
doing the refactoring of the test code
to make sure that you're not refactoring
your test coverage away some some people
told me once that the tests are the
safety net for for refactoring
production code and vice versa so that
the production code is safety net for
for refactoring the test code will you
agree or disagree I agree to a certain
extent the problem with that analogy is
if I refactor my production code and the
tests don't break I was successful if I
refactor my test code and my tests don't
break that doesn't prove that my tests
still work because while the goal of the
production code is to pass all the tests
the goal of the test code is to catch
defects in the production code so the
only way I can really test my tests is
to inject known errors into my
production code and verify that they are
still caught by the tests and the
simplest way to do that is just to you
know if you're suspected test doesn't
work look at whatever it's testing
go into the production code and reverse
an if statement or you know delete a
return statement or an assignment or
something like that and if your tests
don't fail your tests aren't covering
that but that implies going in and
changing the production code now you're
going to throw the changes away but it's
still the act of going into the
production code and deliberately
inserting faults in
- it is how you test the test code when
you're refactoring the test code that
could mean that you have to do a lot of
fault injection into the production code
for it to act as your safety net that
sounds sounds like a next nice
explanation maybe you can do the
injection by some aspect orient X or
whatever but maybe just a very very
rough idea maybe goes beyond beyond the
topic of our talk right now yeah there
is one tool I know of in the enjoy unit
called gesture which will do that it'll
automatically go around and and you know
flip if statements and so on and it
makes one change per cycle to your
production code runs all the tests and
verifies that a test broke and they
don't change is that it does that don't
have a broken test it reports the
problem is you can only if you if you do
more than one change at a time you don't
know which change caused the the actual
test to break and which change is to had
no effect so it's very time-consuming to
run and it's somewhat time consuming to
analyze the output so I don't know a lot
of people who actually go to the trouble
of actually using it in that way so
let's let's come back to to the the
topic of your tutorial about the the
testing patterns and and coats melts so
I saw that that you call them tests
melts so can you tell us more about
those tests shirts tests smells is just
taking the idea of coat smells that was
introduced by martin fowler and kent
back in martin's refactoring book and
applying it to the concept of test code
and there was a paper at one of the
early XP conferences about you know
introducing the idea of test smells and
i introduced a number of these smells
that are typically encountered in test
code and i've taken that idea and sort
of elaborated on it and sort of built a
catalog of the most common test smells
and what to do about them and and use
that as a way to lead people to the
right patterns to apply the test smells
sort of fall into three categories
yes and but by categories I mean it's
around how you discover the smell so
code smells are smells in your test code
that a person reading or writing the
test code will run into so I smell as a
symptom it's got to pass what Martin
calls the sniff test which is it's got
to come and you know the smell has to
come to you
it's the symptom not the root cause so
as an example of a test code smell would
be something I'm sitting there I'm
reading some test code that someone else
wrote and I'm saying oh my god I cannot
understand this code this test code is
really obscure so that is an example of
a code smell obscure test now there's a
whole bunch of reasons why the test
could be obscure but the fact that I'm
having trouble understanding it is the
smell and that's what's motivating me to
think about how I could improve this
test code by applying some test patterns
to it the other two categories are
behavior smells and project smells so
behavior smell is what happens when you
run your tests and something strange
happens say you run the same test
several times in a row and it fails the
first time and passes the next few times
well that's an example of an
unrepeatable test or a test that gives
different results when you run it and
there's several other behavior smells
that are like that and these infer
problems and how you're soft your test
software is written particularly with
respect to how test fixtures are being
managed the third category is project
smells and these are smells that a
project managers likely to see while
observing the software development team
and you know things like they'll see
bugs showing up in production well if
you're doing proper test-driven
development with lots of automated tests
you shouldn't have bugs in production so
what's the root cause of that well the
smell tells you that you need to go look
for the root cause maybe because the
developers aren't writing tests you know
why maybe they weren't given enough time
or the right training or whatever
so that's an example of a project smell
thing I assume you have you have a list
of all those project smells and typical
project smells and you will you will
describe them in more detail in the
tutorial yeah there's a four major
project smells and sort of there's a 19
I think total smells between the code
smells the behavior smells my project
smells and sort of half and half 15 you
know like there's an equal number
roughly of code smells and behavior
smells and then there's these four
project smells that also come in and in
the tutorial I introduce these smells
sort of more of in a case study kind of
format so we'll run into a bunch of code
smells by looking at a test and one by
one we'll go and take each of these code
smells and eliminate them by applying a
certain pattern to eliminate that
specific smell and so then we evolved
the test from being a big ugly hard to
maintain test to a much simpler test and
along the way have introduced a bunch of
different test patterns and then we do
something similar in the behavior smells
section we look at what what are the
symptoms you know that you might run
into and what are the the the root
causes of them and what are the patterns
that you would apply to address those
root causes and those patterns are
called the test patterns right yep
that's what I call X unit test patterns
is these standard ways of structuring
your test code how to manage fixtures
how to do assertions how to make the
software testable those are my design
for testability patterns things like
dependency injection and dependency
lookup and so on so it's all organized
around certain kinds of problems and
what are your choices for addressing
them for example how do you set up a
fixture you can set it up ahead of time
you can set it up at the beginning of
the test run you can set it up at right
at in each test method or in a shared
setup method so there's four or five
different ways of setting up your
fixture each has advantages each has
disadvantages the reason their patterns
is because many people have used each of
them
and the the I use the pattern form to
describe them because patterns are a
good way to express the knowledge the
things to take into consideration so
that people can make an informed choice
as opposed to just me standing there and
saying always do it this way well there
is no single right answer it depends on
the context in which you're operating
sometimes you have to use shared
fixtures shared fixtures have a major
issue around them which is the fact that
you end up with a lot of the behavior
smells and you can eliminate those
behavior smells by always using a fresh
fixture but you can't always afford to
use a fresh fixture in various
circumstances so there's a trade-off
there and what I try and do in each of
the patterns is make the trade-off
explicit what are the indications for
using a particular pattern and what are
the counter indications don't use it in
this circumstance but in this other
circumstance it might make sense and
when you are not sure you want to use
this one here's the other patterns to
solve the same problem and you know go
take a look at those and see if any of
them are more appropriate for your
circumstance than this one so show you
should we go in more detail into some of
those examples I know that it might get
might get hard sometimes to explain code
at the podcast but maybe you can we can
go through these three different kinds
of smells occult smells the behavior
smells and the project smells and maybe
we can take a look at more detail at
some of those smells and so some some
some problems some some more examples so
what do you think about that sure so
let's let's start with an example of a
code smell we already talked about
obscure tests and one of the kinds of
obscure tests one of the reasons for
having an obscure test is if tests have
conditional logic in them my very simple
rule is test methods should have no
conditional logic in them they should be
absolutely linear should be do this do
that do this other thing
verify the outcome test method should
have four
steps for parts of a test setup the
fixture which is sort of the
preconditions of the test which includes
creating the system under test whatever
class or method that you're testing
exercise the system under test by
invoking whatever method you are testing
verifying the outcome and then cleaning
up the the the fixture afterwards every
test should be that simple if you have
conditional logic in your test that's a
symptom of an underlying problem and for
example you might have conditional logic
in the verification of the outcome
because you're not quite sure what the
input to the system was because you
don't have proper control over it the
classic example is if you're doing
something that depends on time and you
need to start looking at the current
system time to figure out what the
expected outcome should be well that's a
symptom that you really should instead
of trying to figure out what the outcome
should be you should be controlling the
input properly by using some techniques
like stubbing out the system clock in
the system the production code so that
the test can get control of a system
time we're passing the time in to the
system under test through the method
signature so any one of those techniques
can be used to avoid the test actually
being several different tests that
depending on when it was run you're
actually testing different parts of the
logic in fact what that points out is if
you need to test how the system behaves
at different times like maybe a.m.
versus p.m. or you know on the hour
versus not on the hour or whatever you
really need separate tests for each of
those to make sure that each of those
scenarios is being run every time and
not just happenstance depending on when
you run the test so the very fact that
you have conditional logic in your test
code tells you something about your
potentially the fact that you're either
missing test conditions or another
symptom is that if the verification of
the outcome is complicated because you
have lists of things that you need to
traverse and therefore you need loops
and stuff well that's how you verify the
outcome
but in your test method you should very
clearly state what the outcome should be
and delegate the how of verifying it to
utility methods custom assertions or
verification methods or other utility
methods like that that build up this
domain-specific library of tests utility
functions that you can call from your
tests and that's what makes your test
both simpler easier to understand and
gives you a single place to modify when
parts of the system under test changed
so you don't have to go back and
refactor hundreds of tests when you make
a change in the production code so what
are typical patterns to solve those
problems well the the most common one
for the latter case where you've got a
say you've got a loop in the in the part
of the test where you're verifying the
outcome because you have a list and you
need to make sure that certain entries
exist in the list and so on well what
you really want to do is take that loop
all that conditional logic do an extract
method on it
and turn it into a custom assertion so
there's no rule that says that only the
writers of J unit or n unit or you know
PI unit or whatever are the only ones
you can write assertion methods anyone
can write assertion methods and the
simplest way to write assertion methods
is to write a bunch of code that does
the assertion say what am I really doing
here the test smell is I've got a bunch
of conditional logic I will get rid of
that smell by extracting that logic from
the test method and putting it into a
test utility method that could be left
on the same class so it's on your test
case class it's just being called from
your various test methods if you want to
reuse it across many tests you can
either use a pull-up refactoring to move
it onto an abstract superclass of your
test case or you can use a move method
to pull it over onto a test utility
class or test helper or object mother or
whatever other class that you want to
create to use as a little sort of
library of utility methods but your
standard little atomic code refactoring
is just applied with a slight twist in
the context of text test code as you
mentioned that the cult smelt and the
conditional logic and these are symptoms
off of some-some
badly designed Tesco maybe I of course
thought about situations where it's
difficult to write tests for and where
you might get more more complicated
conditional logic in test cases like
writing tests for multi-threading code
or garbage collection code or whatever
so so tests that depend on how the
system is executed by the underlying
virtual machine or whatever what do you
think about those those situations well
whenever it's you find that it's hard to
test code it's almost always the root
causes that you're trying to test too
much code at the same time so one of the
things it's important distinction is
unit testing versus sort of functional
testing and in between you know you can
think of testing larger units like
entire components as being you know
slightly different from testing
individual units so if you're doing
test-driven development you might start
off saying I'm gonna write a garbage
collector what are the functional tests
for my garbage collector but then you
need to break that down and say what are
the smaller pieces of my garbage
collector and then what are the
individual classes and methods and
you're writing your unit tests at the
individual class and method level so
when you're testing individual methods
and classes it should be pretty easy to
write your unit tests if your unit tests
are trying to do things like spanning
threads that tells you that you haven't
made your unit small enough and you want
to separate the logic that you're
testing inside the thread from the
testing of the launching of the thread
from the testing of the logic that
decides whether or not or when to launch
the thread so it's just a case of
breaking down your tests into smaller
and smaller pieces they're breaking down
your your system under test into smaller
and smaller pieces that you can then
effectively unit test now to test that
they're all working together properly
when you integrate all these pieces back
again then you're getting into things
that are more component or functional
testing and those are more challenging
to do because you have issues like
you know if I'm launching threads
there's latency involved in that now all
of a sudden my tests have to have delays
on them and as soon as I have delays in
my tests to wait long enough to give the
system time to do that I have problems
with the tests running a lot slower than
they would if they're just running at
sort of CPU speed so the trick is to do
as much of your coverage at the unit
test level where you can test the
details of the logic very exhaustively
and then do just enough testing at the
integration level to verify that the
pieces are connected properly and not to
try and do your exhaustive testing at
that level it's the same thing when
you're testing user interfaces testing
through user interface is notoriously
difficult you know both from an
interfacing perspective the fact that it
user interfaces are tend to be
asynchronous and so the coordination
between the tests and the system under
test and you know multi-threading and
the user interface and so on so it's the
same idea there you want to break it
down into little pieces test the logic
exhaustively at the individual unit
level you know what is the logic that
decides whether or not to enable this
menu item that's a tiny little piece of
logic tiny little test you don't want to
do that at the functional test level
because you're gonna spend a lot of
effort trying to set up the environment
too cause you know that I did to be the
right circumstance in which the menu
item should be either enabled or
disabled and you need several tests and
they're going through this clunky
asynchronous interface and the tests are
going to take a hundred times longer to
run than if you test it at the unit test
level mmm so part of your test strategy
yeah and I talked about this a fair bit
in the book we don't have time in that
in a three-hour tutorial is you know
what kinds of tests to write for what
parts of the system and strategies for
layering your system and decompose it
into smaller pieces to allow the each of
the pieces to be tested independently
and to avoid having to test through
asynchronous interfaces whether it is
user interfaces or messaging interfaces
or multi-threading or whatever so
there's a whole chapter in the book
about design for tested
and how to structure the software to
avoid a lot of these hard to test
situations not cool but it's not part of
the tutorial right yeah in the tutorial
we focus on sort of what are the
specific smells and how to what patterns
to apply to them the design for
testability comes up as solutions to
certain problems but we don't address
the sort of the bigger picture of test
automation strategy because just because
it's too big a topic we could do a whole
tutorial 3-hour tutorial just not that
one topic so I need to expand this from
a single tutorial into a whole tutorial
series that I can offer yeah yeah maybe
a complete testing tutorial series
several days covering different topics
okay so let's come back to the to the
actual tutorial so we talked about code
smells and more details so what about
behavior smells do you have some kind of
your favorite behaviors now well let's
just say that when it comes to behavior
smells it's sort of the favorite in the
sense of the most notorious smells
behavior smells are really insidious
because they they literally come and
bite you in the ass I hope I can say
that on internet radio I know it's not
r-rated or anything
whereas code smells just sort of lie
there and you sort of notice them or if
you you know if you're you know a little
bit sleepy or something you don't really
notice them you just sort of suffer
through them behavior smells really come
and they just come and chase you down
and get you and they bite your leg and
hang on until you do something about
them so the the key thing about behavior
smells is you're running tests and you
don't get the the outputs that you
expected you expected all the tests to
pass but they're not passing and there's
a bunch of different flavors of it the
most common one I call erratic tests and
what that means is that the tests are
behaving erratically sometimes they pass
and sometimes they don't and it all
depends on the circumstance in which you
run them there's a bunch of different
flavors of erratic tests remember the
smell is the symptom and wants you to
start doing some troubleshooting you'll
find the causes so there's a bunch of
different causes there's things like
unrepeatable tests where there's
something in the way the test was coded
that causes it to work the first time
and fail subsequently or fail the first
time and work subsequently and it can be
quite nasty to discover this pattern
because it means somehow you have to
reset things here I'd have to wipe out a
database or close down your test run or
your development environment or
something and then when you start it
again it behaves differently one of the
symptoms is often that it works on the
developers workstation but it fails on
the integration box when it's doing a
rebuild say you're running cruise
control or something like that oh yeah
I've seen this several times yeah but
that same symptom that it works on your
developer box and doesn't work on the
cruise control box could also be a
symptom of a test that is optimistic
about the resources so the resources
aren't that the test depends on it just
assumes they're there it doesn't set
them up from within the test and they're
set up on the developers box but they
were never set up on the integration box
mm-hmm right so there's several
different root causes for that same
symptom that it works in one place or
not in another place another example of
an erratic test is one which works at
certain times of the day or night or
certain you know like it works in 30d
months but it doesn't work in in
February or it works in normal years but
not in leap years because it depends on
calendar math etc and it's using the
current system time as opposed to using
a known time also a lot of these issues
are have to be addressed by the
appropriate use of test stubs or mock
objects to control the inputs of the
system so that you're not dealing with
or left over inputs you know things that
other tests may have modified do you
think that tests that depend on the
state over offer database they also
belong to this category absolutely
because you never know what's going to
be in that database that that root cause
actually leads to several symptoms
several smells one of them is the tests
tend to be obscure because it's not
clear in the test what's in the database
so you're using a magic number like
we're gonna get customer 47 well what's
special about customer 47 and how does
that impact the expected behavior of the
system under test hmm so you get that
smell but then you also get the smell
that it works today but tomorrow someone
changed customer 47 state and now there
are effectively a different customer
from the perspective of this test so the
test fails or someone else wrote a new
test which happens to run before your
tests in the test suite which changes
the state of customer 47 and therefore
your test fails whenever it is run after
this other tests or it runs by itself
but fails when run is a larger group so
these are all examples of erratic tests
either because they're interacting with
each other or because they're optimistic
about resources or because you know
other tests are running at the same time
and so on so there's a whole bunch of
reasons for erratic tests that the the
debugging troubleshooting of this is so
complicated that in the book I've
actually got troubleshooting flowcharts
for a couple of these behavior smells
that sort of leads you through you know
ask in a series of questions to help you
nail down whether this is a case of an
interacting test now there's two tests
interacting with each other at runtime
or whether it's a case of resource
optimism or it's a test run war caused
by some shared resources being you know
shared globally across multiple test
runners or whatever so it's like I said
it's quite a quite a complicated process
to sort it out the good news is that
almost all of those tests can be avoided
by using what I call a fresh fixture
which means every test sets up its own
fixture every time it's run so this is
some some kind of the best
choice tooth pattern yeah it's the fresh
mixture is the pattern that one should
always use if in doubt and unfortunately
a lot of people very quickly jump to
using shared fixtures which is somewhat
you know set up a fixture somewhere and
a whole bunch of tests use it and my
feeling is that people resort to that
solution too easily without
understanding all the ramifications of
it and that's one of the thing that gets
them into trouble and that by suitable
stubbing of the fixture they can avoid
some of the issues caused with fresh
fixtures for example if you have a
database onto your system setting up a
fresh fixture may take longer
therefore you stub out the database so
that it doesn't take longer rather than
going to a shared fixture so that you
don't have to set it up for each test
but that leading to all these
interacting test issues hmm and so these
are the the trade-offs that I talked a
lot about in in the book for each of the
patterns is yeah you can do this and
there works fine in these circumstances
but here's what to watch out for and
here are your alternatives instead of a
shared fixture use a fresh fixture okay
so and the third kind of smell project
smell do you have some kind of your
favorite project smell so the project
smells are once again the smells that a
non developer is likely to observe so an
agile coach a project manager or even
the customer on the project may notice
these smells and the smells are things
like bugs and production code too much
time spent debugging and other things
like that which are sort of things that
you can observe by watching people not
by actually hitting the run button on
your test runner or by actually looking
at test code so let's look at the smell
production bugs what that says is that
everyone's doing the best job they
possibly can but you're still finding
bugs in the production system it could
be in the Quality Assurance like you've
got an independent test group they're
finding bugs or the customers are
finding bugs when they put the code
production and there's a number of
different root causes of that could be
things like the developers aren't
writing all the unit tests and then the
question you have to ask is why aren't
they writing all the unit tests or it
could be that some aspects of the system
can't be tested or that production is
configured differently from the
development environments and so on so
you need to sort of understand you know
do the the the peeling the onion or
asking the five wise to trace your way
back from the symptom to the root cause
that caused it and then you address your
pattern so you apply the appropriate
patterns to address the root cause and
do you have some some kind of test
patterns for those smells as well some
of those patterns sir some of the root
causes of the project smells our
behavior smells and some of them our
code smells so you end up with this sort
of a code smell can lead to a behavior
smell which can then further lead to a
project smell a few of the project
smells are completely that the root
causes are completely separate from the
code and behavior smells for example if
you're finding that the production bugs
are caused by the fact that developers
aren't writing tests and you ask why
aren't they writing the tests and it's
because they're new to writing tests and
they weren't given any training and the
project manager is telling them no no
you got to get the code done don't take
time to learn how to do mocking or
whatever what's this mocking stuff focus
on getting the production code working
then that's your root cause for why you
don't have tests and why your quality is
suffering it's not directly linkable to
a code smell but rather it's it's
linkable to the project managers
behavior and the value system that they
are setting for the team and that's the
root cause that needs to be addressed
once that's out of the way then the
developers can learn how to write the
tests and in the process of doing that
they'll learn the the some of the test
patterns to do a better job of it but
until you remove that impediment of not
being allowed the time to learn it
nothing's going to happen and you're
gonna have production bugs
so I think we talked about those
different kind of smells and some some
typical patterns and so so let's let's
wrap up this a bit and can you give us
some some kind of advice for for
everyday work for everyday practice or
or let's say what should i do tomorrow
and my project well let's assume that
you're you're doing test-driven
development and you know you're you're
open minded and you're prepared to
assume that there are things that can be
improved and there's always something
that can be improved it's just a
question of of what it is so it really
comes down to how do you go about
improving your test code one of the
things that's very easy to do is now
that you have test code do some reviews
on it do some peer reviews there's going
to be different strengths and weaknesses
amongst your development team in coding
of tesco just like there is in coding a
production code and you know unlike
manual unit testing where it's really
hard to review what kind of unit tests a
person actually ran because they were
mostly doing it in a debugger test code
is an asset that you can review and
review the quality of and have you know
share the knowledge of the team with
each other and never have everyone
improved their test coding practices so
sitting down and spending an hour to
reviewing what tests were written and
how the tests actually exercise the
system how easy they are to understand
you know whether they're there's any
inherent problems in them that will lead
to behavior smells and so on is a very
easy exercise to do for a team and will
help everyone's test automation skills
improve so what do you think other some
some some key factors for how to be
successful with this kind of unit
testing and and keeping those tests life
and healthy what I call my recipe for
success is really you have to learn this
stuff incrementally so that means first
you
to write some tests and pick some easy
things that are easy to test testing
legacy code is absolutely the wrong
place to start because it's the hardest
stuff to test because it wasn't designed
for testability so anyone who starts off
a project and says well before I'm gonna
write any new code I'm gonna retrofit a
unit tests onto my legacy code is
setting themselves up for failure focus
on a new part of the system some brand
new component or something and and write
it test first learn how to do testing
there and only once you've got a really
good handle on that back up and try and
retrofit tests onto the legacy part of
the system and then only on an as-needed
basis not don't try and do it sort of
Big Bang let's retrofit test on
everything only as you try and modify
parts of it so that's part one part two
is as you write your tests what you want
to be doing is paying attention to the
test smell so you know have the the list
of code smells and behavior smells handy
and watch for them and just you know one
of these things where awareness is half
the problem just acknowledge that these
problems could exist look for them in
the code you're more likely to find them
and that will help you understand where
the opportunities for improvement are
and then once you've seen a particular
test smell say obscure test figure out
which is the root cause of it and that
will lead your write to what are the
possible solution patterns you can apply
and as you build up your skills for
writing simple test then you can move on
to more complicated scenarios and learn
techniques like stubbing and mocking and
the other test doubles things like
faking out the database for performance
reasons and that kind of stuff and you
what you will find yourself doing is
slowly but surely improving the quality
of the test that you're writing and
really you can think of this as a
continuous improvement program is
applied specifically to your test code
so Thank You Jerrod very very much for
this interview
and our conversation about the X unit
testing patterns was fun talking to you
and good luck for your tutorial
thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
Software Engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details